The Jeff glad to see things are going well and business is starting to pick up
Andrew told me about your outstanding numbers on Tuesday keep up the good work
Now to other business I am gonna suggest a payment schedule
for outstanding money that is due
One can you pay the balance of the license agreement
as soon as possible?
Two I suggest we set up or you suggest what you can pay on the back
Rawties
What do you feel comfortable with?
Paying
Every two weeks
Every month
I would like to keep
I would like to catch up
and maintain current rawties
So if we can start current rawties
and maintain them
Every two weeks as all stores are required to do
I would appreciate it
Let me know if this works for you
Thanks