<tool id="rnazIndex" name="rnazIndex.pl" version="0.1.0">
    <requirements>
        <requirement type="package">rnaz</requirement>
    </requirements>
    <command detect_errors="exit_code"><![CDATA[
        rnazIndex.pl
    ]]></command>
    <inputs>
        <param type="data" name="input1" format="" />
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data name="output1" format="data" from_work_dir="exout" />
    </outputs>
    <tests>
        <test>
            <param name="input1" value="exin"/>
            <output name="output1" file="exout"/>
        </test>
    </tests>
    <help><![CDATA[
        Usage:
     rnazIndex.pl [options] [file]

Options:
    -g, --gff
            Generate GFF formatted output.

    -b, --bed
            Generate BED formatted output.

    -c #:LABEL, --col #:LABEL
            Append a column named LABEL to the HTML-table holding the data
            from the input file column with index #. e.g. "rnazIndex.pl
            --html --col 19:Alifoldz --col 20:RNAmicro annotated.dat"

    -f, --fasta
            Get sequences in FASTA format for loci or windows. See options
            "--seq-dir", "--forward", "--reverse"!

    --seq-dir
            Directory with sequence files. You only need this for FASTA
            output (see option "--fasta"). The files should be named with
            the sequence identifier and the extension ".fa" or ".fasta". If
            your identifier in your input file is for example "contig100"
            then you should have a file named "contig100.fa". (If your
            identifier is of the form ``assembly.chromosome" as for example
            used by UCSC alignments, it is also possible to name the file
            "chr22.fa" for a sequence identifier "hg17.chr22").

    --forward, --reverse
            Only relevant for FASTA output (see option "--fasta"). You can
            set if you want the forward or reverse complement of the
            sequence corresponding to a locus. Since loci don't have strand
            information you might consider both strands for further
            analysis. Windows have strand information, so if you export
            windows as FASTA these options are ignored.

    --ucsc  In UCSC MAF alignment files it is common to use sequence
            identifiers like for example ``hg17.chr22". However, in BED are
            usually specific for a given assembly and therefore only
            ``chr22" is used in the BED files. With this option you change
            any identifier of the form ``X.Y" into ``Y". Moreover, the
            scores are multiplied by 1000 and rounded to integers since the
            UCSC genome browser expects scores between 0 and 1000.

    -l, --loci
            Use the locus information to generate the lines for the GFF and
            BED files. This is the default.

    -w, --windows
            Print the "windows" and not the "loci". Probably, rarely used
            function.

    --html  With this option you get a HTML table which links to the the
            HTML pages which you can create by using the "--html" option in
            "rnazCluster.pl". Redirect the output to some file which resides
            in the "results" directory created by "rnazCluster.pl" and open
            the file with your favourite web-browser.

    -h, --help
            Prints a short help message and exits.

    --man   Prints a detailed manual page and exits.


    ]]></help>
    <citations>
        <citation type="bibtex">
@misc{githubrnaz.git,
  author = {LastTODO, FirstTODO},
  year = {TODO},
  title = {rnaz.git},
  publisher = {GitHub},
  journal = {GitHub repository},
  url = {git@github.com:wash/rnaz.git},
}</citation>
    </citations>
</tool>