<tool id="rnazWindow" name="rnazWindow.pl" version="0.1.0">
  <requirements>
    <requirement type="package">rnaz</requirement>
  </requirements>
  <command detect_errors="exit_code"><![CDATA[
  rnazWindow.pl


  ]]></command>
  <inputs>
    <param format="txt" name="input" type="data" label="Input Alignment File" />
    <param name="forward_or_reverse" type="select" label="Scored strand">
      <option value="forward">Score forward strand (-f)</option>
      <option value="reverse">Score reverse strand (-r)</option>
      <option value="both-strands">Score both strands (-b)</option>
    </param>

  </inputs>
  <outputs>
    <data name="output1" format="data" from_work_dir="exout" />
  </outputs>
  <tests>
    <test>
      <param name="input1" value="exin"/>
      <output name="output1" file="exout"/>
    </test>
  </tests>
  <help><![CDATA[
  RNAz cannot score alignments longer than 400 columns. In practice, it is generally
  advisable that you score long alignments, say > 200 columns, in shorter, overlapping
  windows.  For general purpose screens we recommend a window size of 120.  This
  window size appears large enough to detect local secondary structures within long
  ncRNAs and, on the other hand, small enough to find short secondary structures
  without loosing the signal in a much too long window
  
  Usage:
  rnazWindow.pl [options] [file]

  Options:
  -w, --window=N
  Size of the window (Default: 120)

  -s, --slide=N
  Step size (Default: 120)

  -m, --max-length
  Slice only alignments longer than N columns. This means blocks
  longer than the window size given by --window but shorter than N
  are kept intact and not sliced. Per default this length is set
  to the window size given by --window (or 120 by default).

  --max-gap=X
  Maximum fraction of gaps. If a reference sequence is used (i.e.
  "--no-reference" is not set), each sequence is compared to the
  reference sequence and if in the pairwise comparison the
  fraction of columns with gaps is higher than X the sequence is
  discarded. If no reference sequence is used, all sequences with
  a fraction of gaps higher than X are discarded. (Default: 0.25)

  --max-masked=X
  Maximum fraction of masked (=lowercase letters) in a sequence.
  All sequences with a fraction of more than X lowercase letters
  are discarded. This is usually used for excluding repeat
  sequences marked by "RepeatMasker" but any other information can
  be encoded by using lowercase letters. (Default: 0.1)

  --min-id=X
  Discard alignment windows with an overall mean pairwise identity
  smaller than X%. (Default: 50)

  --min-seqs=N
  Minimum number of sequences in an alignment. Discard any windows
  with less than N sequences (Default:2).

  --max-seqs=N
  Maximum number of sequences in an alignment. If the number of
  sequences in a window is higher than N, a subset of sequences is
  used with exactly N sequences. The greedy algorithm of the
  program "rnazSelectSeqs.pl" is used which optimizes for a user
  specified mean pairwise identity (see "--opt-id"). (Default: 6)

  --num-samples=N
  Number of different subsets of sequences that is sampled if
  there are more sequences in the alignment than "--max-seqs".
  (Default: 1)

  --min-length=N
  Minimum number of columns of an alignment slice. After removing
  sequences from the alignment, ``all-gap" columns are removed. If
  the resulting alignment has fewer than N columns, the complete
  alignment is discarded.

  --opt-id=X
  If the number of sequences has to be reduced (see "--max-seqs")
  a subset of sequences is chosen which is optimized for this
  value of mean pairwise identity. (In percent, default: 80)

  --max-id=X
  One sequence from pairs with pairwise identity higher than X %
  this is removed (default: 99, i.e. only almost identical
  sequences are removed) NOT IMPLEMENTED

  --forward
  --reverse
  --both-strands
  Output forward, reverse complement or both of the sequences in
  the windows. Please note: "RNAz" has the same options, so if you
  use "rnazWindow.pl" for an RNAz screen, we recommend to set the
  option directly in "RNAz" and leave the default here. (Default:
  ---forward)

  --no-reference
  By default the first sequence is interpreted as reference
  sequence. This means, for example, that if the reference
  sequence is removed during filtering steps the complete
  alignment is discarded. Also, if there are too many sequences in
  the alignment, the reference sequence is never removed when
  choosing an appropriate subset. Having a reference sequence is
  crucial if you are doing screens of genomic regions. For some
  other applications it might not be necessary and in such cases
  you can change the default behaviour by setting this option.

  --verbose
  Verbose output on STDERR, describing all performed filtering
  steps.

  -v, --version
  Prints version information and exits.

  -h, --help
  Prints a short help message and exits.

  --man   Prints a detailed manual page and exits.


  ]]></help>
  <citations>
    <citation type="bibtex">
	  @misc{githubrnaz.git,
	  author = {LastTODO, FirstTODO},
	  year = {TODO},
	  title = {rnaz.git},
	  publisher = {GitHub},
	  journal = {GitHub repository},
	  url = {git@github.com:wash/rnaz.git},
	}</citation>
  </citations>
</tool>
