<tool id="mcl_clustering" name="MCL"  version="14.137">
    <description>A Markov Cluster Algorithm.</description>
    <requirements>
        <requirement type="package" version="14.137">mcl</requirement>
    </requirements>
    <command detect_errors="aggressive">
<![CDATA[
    mcl
        $infile
        --abc
        -I $inflation
        -o $outfile
        -scheme $scheme
        -pi $pi
        -ph $ph
        -if $if
        --discard-loops=$discard_loops
]]>
    </command>
        <inputs>
            <param name="infile" type="data" format="tabular" label="MCL Label input"/>

            <param name="inflation" type="float" value="4.0" label="Main inflation value (-I)"
                help="This value is the main handle for affecting cluster granularity. It is usually chosen somewhere in the range [1.2-5.0]. -I 5.0 will tend to result in fine-grained clusterings, and -I 1.2 will tend to result in very coarse grained clusterings."/>
            <param name="pi" type="float" label="pre-inflation (-pi)" value="3.0" help=""/>
            <param name="ph" type="float" label="pre-inflation, max-bound (-ph)" value="3.0" help=""/>
            <param name="if" type="float" label="start-inflation (-if)" value="3.0" help=""/>

            <param name="discard_loops" truevalue="y" falsevalue="n" checked="True" type="boolean"
                label="remove any loops that are present in the input" help=""/>

            <param name="scheme" type="select" label="Resource schemes (-scheme)"
                help="High schemes result in more expensive computations that may possibly be more accurate.">
                <option value="1">1</option>
                <option value="2">2</option>
                <option value="3">3</option>
                <option value="4" selected="true">4</option>
                <option value="5">5</option>
                <option value="6">6</option>
                <option value="7">7</option>
            </param>

        </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data format="tabular" name="outfile" label="MCS on ${on_string}" />
    </outputs>
    <tests>
        <test>
            <param name="infile" value="sample_input.tabular" ftype="tabular" />
            <param name="inflation" value="2.0" />
            <param name="scheme" value="4" />
            <output name="outfile" file="mcl_result_01.tabular" ftype="tabular"/>
        </test>
    </tests>
    <help>
<![CDATA[

**What it does**

The Markov Cluster Algorithm, aka the MCL algorithm.

This program implements mcl, a cluster algorithm for graphs.
A single parameter controls the granularity of the output clustering, namely the -I inflation option described further below.
In standard usage of the program this parameter is the only one that may require changing.
By default it is set to 2.0 and this is a good way to start. If you want to explore cluster structure in graphs with MCL,
vary this parameter to obtain clusterings at different levels of granularity. A good set of starting values is 1.4, 2, 4, and 6.

**Example input (Label input)**

::

    cat hat 0.2
    hat bat 0.16
    bat cat 1.0
    bat bit 0.125
    bit fit 0.25
    fit hit 0.5
    hit bit 0.16


----------
References
----------

If you use MCL-edge software in your research, please cite it as you would cite a journal or a book. 
This includes papers published in regular or electronic journals, usage of MCL-edge as a back-end to a database that is accessible via a web interface,
or inclusion of MCL-edge in a larger framework of software that is distributed for other people to use. Include at least one of the following citations:

Stijn van Dongen, Graph Clustering by Flow Simulation, PhD thesis, University of Utrecht, May 2000.
( http://www.library.uu.nl/digiarchief/dip/diss/1895620/inhoud.htm )

Stijn van Dongen, A cluster algorithm for graphs, Technical Report INS-R0010, National Research Institute for Mathematics and Computer Science in the Netherlands, Amsterdam, May 2000.
( http://www.cwi.nl/ftp/CWIreports/INS/INS-R0010.ps.Z )

Stijn van Dongen, Graph clustering via a discrete uncoupling process, Siam Journal on Matrix Analysis and Applications 30-1, p121-141, 2008.

Stijn van Dongen and Cei Abreu-Goodger, Using MCL to extract clusters from networks, in Bacterial Molecular Networks: Methods and Protocols, Methods in Molecular Biology, Vol 804, pages 281—295 (2012). PMID 22144159.

and add proper attributions to the MCL-edge home page http://micans.org/mcl/. For biological applications, it is appropriate to cite, additionally, the reference article for the first application of MCL to biological data:

Enright A.J., Van Dongen S., Ouzounis C.A., An efficient algorithm for large-scale detection of protein families, Nucleic Acids Research 30(7):1575-1584 (2002).


**Galaxy Wrapper Author**::

    *  Bjoern Gruening, University of Freiburg
    *  Pavan Videm , University of Freiburg

]]>
    </help>
</tool>
