<tool id="bgruening_general_mapping" name="General Mapping Tool" version="0.1">
  <description>maps an id to several datasets</description>
  <command interpreter="python">
<![CDATA[
    general_mapping.py --mapping ${mapping.fields.path} --query $infile -o $outfile -c $column
]]>
  </command>
  <inputs>
    <param name="infile" type="data" format="tabular" label="File with UniProt Accession Numbers"/>
    <param name="column" label="Column with UniProt Accession Numbers" type="data_column" data_ref="infile" accept_default="true" />
        <param name="mapping" type="select" label="Mapping Table">
            <options from_file="mapping.loc">
              <column name="value" index="0"/>
              <column name="name" index="1"/>
              <column name="path" index="2"/>
            </options>
        </param>
  </inputs>
  <outputs>
    <data format="tabular" name="outfile" />
  </outputs>
  <help>
<![CDATA[
**What it does**

That tool represents a general mapping tool. Insert some ids and get back all related entities.

.. class:: infomark

If you would like to include a new mapping file, please contact your system administrator. It should be really easy to include new mapping files. A few examples you can find in `github`_.
Any questions? Please contact `me`_.

.. _me: bjoern.gruening@gmail.com
.. _github: https://github.com/bgruening/galaxytools/tree/master/file_manipulation/tools


*******
Example
*******
======================
Gene Association (GOA)
======================

Description of the GOA Mapping file, if it is not present in your selection please contact your galaxy administrator.

1. **DB**

   Database from which annotated entry has been taken.
   For the UniProtKB and UniProtKB Complete Proteomes gene associaton files: UniProtKB
   For the PDB association file:  PDB
   Example: UniProtKB

2. **DB_Object_ID**

   A unique identifier in the database for the item being annotated.
   Here: an accession number or identifier of the annotated protein
   (or PDB entry for the gene_association.goa_pdb file)
   For the UniProtKB and UniProtKB Complete Proteomes gene association files: a UniProtKB Accession.
   Examples O00165

3.  **DB_Object_Symbol**

    A (unique and valid) symbol (gene name) that corresponds to the DB_Object_ID.
    An officially approved gene symbol will be used in this field when available.
    Alternatively, other gene symbols or locus names are applied.
    If no symbols are available, the identifier applied in column 2 will be used.
    Examples: G6PC
    CYB561
    MGCQ309F3

4.  **Qualifier**

    This column is used for flags that modify the interpretation of an
    annotation.
    If not null, then values in this field can equal: NOT, colocalizes_with, contributes_to,
    NOT | contributes_to, NOT | colocalizes_with
    Example: NOT

5.  **GO ID**

    The GO identifier for the term attributed to the DB_Object_ID.
    Example: GO:0005634

6.  **DB:Reference**

    A single reference cited to support an annotation.
    Where an annotation cannot reference a paper, this field will contain
    a GO_REF identifier. See section 8 and
    http://www.geneontology.org/doc/GO.references
    for an explanation of the reference types used.
    Examples: PMID:9058808
    DOI:10.1046/j.1469-8137.2001.00150.x
    GO_REF:0000002
    GO_REF:0000020
    GO_REF:0000004
    GO_REF:0000003
    GO_REF:0000019
    GO_REF:0000023
    GO_REF:0000024
    GO_REF:0000033

7.  **Evidence**

    One of either EXP, IMP, IC, IGI, IPI, ISS, IDA, IEP, IEA, TAS, NAS,
    NR, ND or RCA.
    Example: TAS

8.  **With**

    An additional identifier to support annotations using certain
    evidence codes (including IEA, IPI, IGI, IMP, IC and ISS evidences).
    Examples: UniProtKB:O00341
    InterPro:IPROO1878
    RGD:123456
    CHEBI:12345
    Ensembl:ENSG00000136141
    GO:0000001
    EC:3.1.22.1

9.  **Aspect**

    One of the three ontologies, corresponding to the GO identifier applied.
    P (biological process), F (molecular function) or C (cellular component).
    Example: P

10. **DB_Object_Name**

    Name of protein
    The full UniProt protein name will be present here,
    if available from UniProtKB. If a name cannot be added, this field
    will be left empty.
    Examples: Glucose-6-phosphatase
    Cellular tumor antigen p53
    Coatomer subunit beta

11. **Synonym**

    Gene_symbol [or other text]
    Alternative gene symbol(s), IPI identifier(s) and UniProtKB/Swiss-Prot identifiers are
    provided pipe-separated, if available from UniProtKB. If none of these identifiers
    have been supplied, the field will be left empty.
    Example:  RNF20|BRE1A|IPI00690596|BRE1A_BOVIN
    IPI00706050
    MMP-16|IPI00689864

12. **DB_Object_Type**

    What kind of entity is being annotated.
    Here: protein (or protein_structure for the
    gene_association.goa_pdb file).
    Example: protein

13. **Taxon_ID**

    Identifier for the species being annotated.
    Example: taxon:9606

14. **Date**

    The date of last annotation update in the format 'YYYYMMDD'
    Example: 20050101

15. **Assigned_By**

    Attribute describing the source of the annotation.  One of
    either UniProtKB, AgBase, BHF-UCL, CGD, DictyBase, EcoCyc, EcoWiki, Ensembl,
    FlyBase, GDB, GeneDB_Spombe,GeneDB_Pfal, GOC, GR (Gramene), HGNC, Human Protein Atlas,
    JCVI, IntAct, InterPro, LIFEdb, PAMGO_GAT, MGI, Reactome, RGD,
    Roslin Institute, SGD, TAIR, TIGR, ZFIN, PINC (Proteome Inc.) or WormBase.
    Example: UniProtKB

16. **Annotation_Extension**

    Contains cross references to other ontologies/databases that can be used to qualify or
    enhance the GO term applied in the annotation.
    The cross-reference is prefaced by an appropriate GO relationship; references to multiple ontologies
    can be entered.
    Example: part_of(CL:0000084)
    occurs_in(GO:0009536)
    has_input(CHEBI:15422)
    has_output(CHEBI:16761)
    has_participant(UniProtKB:Q08722)
    part_of(CL:0000017)|part_of(MA:0000415)

17. **Gene_Product_Form_ID**

    The unique identifier of a specific spliceform of the protein described in column 2 (DB_Object_ID)
    Example:O43526-2


]]>
  </help>
</tool>
 
